You know the feeling you get
when you learn something new
about a health problem
you’ve been trying to reverse?
Maybe high blood pressure,
diabetes, or heart disease.
Well, there’s nothing I like better
than bringing you the information
that will help you do just that.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
There are a variety of unique
health issues that women face
that affect their quality of life.
And today we start
with one way to treat
one of the most debilitating diseases
that women face: endometriosis.
Endometriosis is a
major cause of disability
and compromised quality of life
among women — a chronic disease
which is under-diagnosed, under-
reported, under-researched.
For patients it can be a nightmare
of misinformation, myths, taboos,
lack of diagnosis, and problematic
hit-and-miss treatments,
overlaid by a painful, chronic,
stubborn disease.
Pain is what best characterizes
the disease,
pain, painful intercourse, heavy
irregular periods and infertility.
About one in a dozen
young women suffer,
and it accounts for about half the
cases of pelvic pain and infertility.
It's caused by what's called
retrograde menstruation.
Instead of the blood going down,
it goes up into the abdominal cavity,
where bleeding tissue of the uterine
lining can implant onto other organs.
You can have the lesions
surgically removed,
but the recurrence rate within
five years is as high as 50%.
Now, endometriosis is an
estrogen-dependent disease,
so might the anti-estrogenic
effects of the phytoestrogens
in flaxseeds and soy foods help,
as they appear to in breast cancer?
I couldn't find studies on flax, but
soy food consumption may indeed
reduce the risk
of endometriosis,
but I couldn't find any studies
on treating the disease with soy.
There's another food,
though, associated
with decreased breast
cancer risk: seaweed.
Seaweeds have special types
of fiber and phytonutrients
not found among land plants,
so it's not like choosing
to get your beta-carotene from
a carrot versus a sweet potato.
If you want these unique
seaweed components,
some of which may have
anti-cancer properties,
we need to find a way to incorporate
sea vegetables into our diets —
anti-cancer properties such
as anti-estrogen effects.
Japanese women have among
the lowest rates of breast,
endometrial, and
ovarian cancers.
They have longer menstrual cycles
and lower estrogen levels
circulating in their blood
and that may help account
for their low risk of
estrogen-dependent cancers.
We assumed this was their soy intake,
but the seaweed might be helping as well.
You can drip seaweed broth on
human ovary cells that make estrogen
and see estrogen levels
drop, because it's either
inhibiting production or facilitating
breakdown of estrogen,
and may even block
estrogen receptors,
lowering the activity of the
estrogen you do produce.
This is in a Petri dish, though,
but it happens in women as well.
They estimate that an effective
estrogen-lowering dose of seaweed
for an average American woman
might be around 5 grams a day,
but no one has apparently tried
testing it on cancer patients yet,
but it has been tried
on endometriosis.
Three women with abnormal cycles—
two of which with endometriosis—
volunteered to add a tiny amount
of dried powdered bladderwrack,
a common seaweed,
to their daily diet.
It effectively lengthened their cycles
and reduced the duration of their periods.
And not just by a little.
Check out subject number 1.
A 30-year history of irregular periods,
averaging every 16 days,
but adding just a quarter teaspoon
of this seaweed powder a day
added 10 days onto
her cycle, up to 26 days,
and a half teaspoon a day
brought her up to like 31,
nearly doubling the
length of her cycle.
And they all experienced marked
reductions in blood flow
and a decreased duration
of menstruation.
Poor subject number 1 was
having periods every 16 days
that lasted 9 days long.
Can you imagine?
After 30 years of this kind of craziness,
just a half teaspoon of seaweed a day
and she was having periods just once
a month and only lasting about 4 days.
And most importantly, in the two
women suffering from endometriosis,
they reported substantial
alleviation of their pain.
How is that possible?
Look at their drop in estrogen levels.
A 75% drop after just a quarter
teaspoon of seaweed powder a day,
85% after a half teaspoon.
Now obviously with just a couple
women, no control group,
we have to do bigger
better studies.
But look when this study was
published: more than a decade ago
and not a single such study
has been published since.
Does the research world
just not care about women?
Millions of women are suffering
with these conditions.
Who's going to fund it, though?
That much seaweed costs
less than 5 pennies,
so a larger study
may never be done.
But with no downsides, I would suggest
endometriosis sufferers give it a try.
In our next story,
we look at how oxidized
cholesterol found in eggs,
processed meat,
and parmesan cheese
can have cancer-fueling estrogenic
effects on human breast cancer.
In 1908, the presence of
cholesterol crystals was noted
in the proliferating areas of cancers,
suggesting that perhaps cholesterol,
in some way, was associated with
the regulation of cancer proliferation.
A century later we now recognize
the accumulation of cholesterol
as a general feature of cancer tissue,
and recent evidence suggests
that cholesterol
may indeed play critical roles
in the progression of cancers,
including breast, prostate,
and colorectal cancers.
Perhaps that could explain why
egg consumption was associated
with increased breast cancer risk.
And indeed, a systematic review
of the evidence suggests
that dietary cholesterol intake
increases risk of breast cancer,
and the more cholesterol you eat,
the higher the risk appears to go.
But why?
One thought is that the prolonged
ingestion of a cholesterol-enriched diet
induces a chronic auto-
inflammatory response,
and we know that chronic
inflammation can lead
to the initiation, promotion, and
progression of tumor development.
It's true that sprinkling some
cholesterol on white blood cells
in a test tube can trigger the release
of inflammatory compounds,
and LDL cholesterol can induce breast
cancer proliferation and invasion.
But again that's in vitro, where you
can show that like breast cancer cells
can migrate nearly twice as
far within a day in a petri dish
in the presence of LDL cholesterol.
But what about in people?
Well, the level of LDL cholesterol
in the blood of women
diagnosed with breast
cancer does appear to be
a predictive factor
of tumor progression.
About two years after
surgery/chemo/radiation,
not one of the women in the lowest
third of LDL cholesterol levels
had a cancer recurrence.
The same could not be said for
women with higher cholesterol.
We know cholesterol can cause
inflammation in our artery walls.
Maybe it's also playing an effect on
breast cancer initiation and progression?
They speculate that the high cholesterol
levels may have a cancer-fueling effect.
And indeed, women
with breast cancer
who happen to be taking
cholesterol-lowering statin drugs
appear to live about 40% longer
before the cancer comes back.
But the data isn't good enough to ensure
the drug benefits outweigh the risks,
though lowering cholesterol
with diet one may be able to get
the best of both worlds.
But what does that have to
do with dietary cholesterol?
Sure, animal studies show that
if you feed mice cholesterol
you can accelerate their cancers,
but extrapolation to humans
is difficult as dietary cholesterol
has limited effects
on blood cholesterol
levels in humans.
Thus, dietary cholesterol might
just be indicative of a lifestyle
prone to health-related
problems, including cancer.
Maybe people are just more likely
to chase bacon and eggs down
with a cigarette
compared to oatmeal?
It's hard to imagine how
dietary cholesterol alone
could promote cancer development.
But that all changed recently with the
discovery that 27-Hydroxycholesterol,
a metabolite of cholesterol,
can function as an estrogen
and increase the proliferation
of most breast cancer cells.
Ah, so it's not the cholesterol itself,
but what it turns into in the body.
Scientists have long struggled
to understand why women
with heart disease risk factors are
more likely to develop breast cancer.
Now, perhaps we know.
The discovery that the most abundant
oxidized cholesterol metabolite
in our bloodstream can
have estrogenic effects
may explain the link between high
cholesterol and the development
and progression of breast
cancer and prostate cancer.
Yes, 27-Hydroxycholesterol
also stimulates the proliferation
of prostate cancer cells, boosting
growth by about 50 percent.
I've explored before the role
oxycholesterols may play
in mediating pro-oxidative and
pro-inflammatory processes
in degenerative diseases such as
Alzheimer's and heart disease,
but now it looks like oxidized
cholesterol can play a role
in all three stages of tumor
development as well:
initiation, promotion, and then
the progression of the cancer.
Not just promoting the growth
of breast cancer cells,
but also inducing their
invasion and migration,
potentially facilitating breast
cancer metastasis
through suppressing
anti-cancer immunity,
and then inducing angiogenesis:
helping breast tumors hook
up their blood supply.
This is all supported by
several lines of evidence
that point to a pathologic role
for this cholesterol metabolite.
Yeah, you can feed
mice cholesterol,
their oxysterol levels go up
and their tumors accelerate.
It also appears to dramatically
hasten the spread, or metastasis,
of breast tumors to other organs.
But turning to human
breast tissue samples,
they found that more aggressive
tumors have higher levels
of the enzyme that converts
cholesterol into 27-HC.
In breast cancer patients with estrogen
receptor-positive tumors, the 27
Hydroxycholesterol content in their
breast tissue is increased overall,
and especially within
the tumor itself,
so much so that
circulating oxysterol levels
in the blood may one day
be used as a prognostic factor.
And breast cancer patients with low tumor
levels of the enzyme that breaks down
27-HC did not live as long as
women who can detoxify it better.
The bottom line is that some estrogen-
driven breast tumors may rely
on 27-HC to grow when
estrogen isn't available.
And that may explain a second
breast cancer mystery.
Over 80% of breast cancers start
out responding to estrogen,
and so what we do is
use hormone blockers,
either aromatase inhibitors to stop the
formation of estrogen in the first place,
or tamoxifen to block its action.
Despite the efficacy of these drugs, many
patients relapse with resistant tumors.
And that's where oxidized
cholesterol can come in.
27-HC can fuel breast cancer
growth without estrogen,
which could explain why sometimes
these estrogen blockers don't work.
And finally, 27-HC may explain
why breast cancer patients
with higher vitamin D levels
appear to live longer.
Vitamin D supplementation
decreases 27-HC levels in the blood.
The best way, though, may be
to just lower overall cholesterol.
Lower cholesterol, and you
lower oxidized cholesterol.
So discovering this role of cholesterol
is actually really good news,
since cholesterol is a highly
amenable risk factor,
either by lifestyle, dietary,
or pharmacologic interventions.
The implications of these findings,
according to the principal investigator,
is that lowering cholesterol with
dietary changes or drugs
could reduce a women's breast
cancer risk or slow tumor growth.
Finally, when it comes
to uterine fibroids,
is soy helpful,
harmful, or harmless?
About 1 in 4 women will
eventually suffer from fibroids,
most commonly manifesting
as excessively
heavy periods and pain or pressure.
Why might you feel pressure?
Because you may be carrying
around 26 pounds
of tumors in your uterus.
Fibroids are the most common
reason women get hysterectomies—
having their uterus removed completely,
a major surgery associated
with disability and death,
but all surgery carries risk.
The chances of dying
within a month of surgery
may only be about 1 in 1200,
which makes it among
our safest surgeries,
safer than getting your
gallbladder removed, for example.
But, of course, you lose the
ability to bear children,
and costs billions of dollars a year.
Yet, despite the high prevalence,
significant pain and suffering,
and huge economic impact,
relatively little is
understood about the cause
and disease process that
lead to fibroid tumors.
Avoiding atomic bomb
blasts whenever you can
is probably a good idea in terms
of decreasing fibroids risk,
but what about more easily
modifiable risk factors?
Well, alcohol consumption is associated
with increased risk, particularly beer,
and whenever you hear that,
whenever you hear beer specifically,
you think of the hormonal
effects specific to beer,
specifically the powerful
phytoestrogen found in hops.
Well, if that phytoestrogen
is increasing fibroids risk,
what about the phytoestrogens in soy?
Well, this was looked at in
the Black Women’s Health Study.
Fibroids are 2 to 3 times more prevalent
among African-American women;
so, they thought maybe dairy intake
might be contributing to the disparity,
given their higher levels
of lactose intolerance.
And indeed, dairy consumption
was associated with reduced risk.
They figured it was the calcium content
or maybe the vitamin D,
but perhaps the women
were drinking soy milk
instead and that was
increasing their risk?
No, soy intake was found
to be unrelated,
same finding in a group of
predominantly white women,
though they did note
a protective association
with the amount of lignans
flowing through their bodies.
Lignans are another
class of phytoestrogens
found predominantly in flaxseeds,
but throughout the plant kingdom.
Hard to make any generalizations
about soy phytoestrogens, though,
as soy consumption was
rather low across the board.
This was done in Washington state.
If you go to Japan,
where they have the highest per capita
soy consumption in the world,
you could get a bigger spread of intakes.
The researchers had previously found
that soy intake was inversely associated
with the risk of hysterectomy,
meaning women who ate more soy
had lower hysterectomy rates,
suggesting a potentially protective effect
of soy against uterine fibroids,
since that’s the main reason
women have their uterus removed.
This would be consistent
with in vitro studies
that found that the
main soy phytoestrogen
seemed to inhibit fibroid tissue
proliferation in a petri dish.
But, when they specifically looked,
there was no evidence of
a link to soy at all,
protective or otherwise.
The same was found in
one study out of China.
Fruit and vegetable intake
was associated with
significantly lower risk of fibroids,
but soy food consumption was not.
But a second study out of China,
published the same year,
found a significant association
between soymilk intake and fibroids.
That’s consistent with the
three alarming case reports
of women with symptomatic fibroids
reporting an “unusually”
high intake of soymilk,
or regularly consuming
“excessive” amounts of soy,
or “extremely high” intakes of soy
every day for decades.
It's hard to take these cases seriously
when nowhere do they actually say
how much they were consuming.
The only quantitative mention
was 40 grams of isoflavones,
which roughly translates to 400 gallons
of soymilk every day—
that would be excessive,
but also impossible.
The only way to know for sure
is to put it to the test.
Not just a population
study or anecdotal reports
but randomize women to two
years of soy phytoestrogens—
the amount found in 3 to
5 cups of soymilk a day—
and no significant effect
on the frequency or growth
of fibroids was found.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Stay tuned for December 5, 2023
for the launch of my new one,
How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.